Guide to the Horace Trumbauer Architectural Drawings Collection, 1924 - 1958
University Archives Duke University
Horace Trumbauer Architectural Drawings collection 1924 - 1958
Trumbauer, Horace, 1869-1938.
9 Linear Feet 6000 Items
University Archives, Duke University
From 1924 through 1958 the architectural firm of Horace Trumbauer of Philadelphia, Pa. was hired to design much of Duke University's East and West campuses. Horace Trumbauer, William O. Frank, and Julian Abele were the firm's main designers. Frank Clyde Brown, S.W. Myatt and A.C. Lee were administrators of construction at Duke University during this time. Some of the buildings designed by the firm are the Duke University Chapel, the Allen Administration Building, Cameron Indoor Stadium, Baldwin Auditorium, the East Campus Union Building, the East Campus Central Heating Plant Complex, the Carr Building (formerly known as the Class Room Building), the Medical School and Hospital, the Nurses' Home, the Law School, the School of Religion, the Chemistry Building, and the Botany and Biology Building. The firm also designed the Giles, Alspaugh, Pegram, Bassett, and Brown residence halls (formerly known as Dormitories 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5, respectively). Included in the collection are blueprints, photographs, sketches, drawings, written material, and printed material relating to the planning and construction of buildings at Duke University from 1924 to 1958.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
No restrictions.
Provenance
The Horace Trumbauer Architectural Drawings were received by the University Archives as a transfer, date unknown.
Biographical Note
Horace Trumbauer
Born in the Frankford section of Philadelphia in 1868, Horace Trumbauer left school at the age of fourteen and entered the architectural firm of G. W. and W. D. Hewitt as an "errand boy". He was soon promoted to draftsman. Trumbauer's advancement and acquisition of knowledge enabled him to eventually open his own office in 1890.
Trumbauer's first major commission was a mansion in Glenside, Pennsylvania, for sugar baron William Welsh Harrison. When Harrison's mansion burned to the ground in 1893, he commissioned Trumbauer to rebuild it. This second home, called Grey Towers (now part of Arcadia University), marked Trumbauer's rise to prominence in the profession. Its castle-like design instilled the estate with a distinct architectural style that was unique to Trumbauer's work.
Trumbauer's firm expanded its scope, designing not only mansions in Philadelphia, New York City, and Newport, Rhode Island, but also apartment houses and other large structures. By 1904, when the prominent Architectural Record published a lengthy account of Trumbauer's works, he had become one of the country's most distinguished architects. Over the next decades, Trumbauer and his staff received more than 1,000 commissions, including the Philadelphia Museum of Art, and many offices, schools, hotels, and medical buildings. Among Trumbauer's most important commissions of this period was the Gothic revival Duke University campus in Durham, North Carolina.
Because of his talent and aloofness, Trumbauer gained accolades in New York City before he did in his hometown. His colleagues in Philadelphia did not elect him to membership in their chapter of the American Institute of Architects (AIA) until 1931, an affront that reportedly greatly disturbed him. Added to this mix was the fact that he employed, advanced and befriended one of the very few African American architects in the country. Trumbauer and Abele each faced discrimination and because of that Trumbauer empathized with the racial discrimination confronting Abele. Consequently they forged a close relationship based on respect for talent and friendship, but each also trapped the other in a peculiar set of circumstances. Trumbauer excelled as the front man dealing with major clients but he avoided publicity and public appearances. Abele was the African American chief designer essential to the internal operation of the firm, a position too confining for his deserved reputation. Abele, himself, was not elected to membership in the Philadelphia AIA until 1941.
Trumbauer worked exclusively in period styles, reviving the architecture of distant times and places. Due to architectural trends and the Great Depression, Trumbauer's practice dwindled in the 1930s. His staff fell from a high of thirty members down to his longtime associates Julian Abele and William O. Frank, and a few others. He died on September 18, 1938.
Julian Abele
Born in Philadelphia in 1881, Julian Abele was the youngest of eight children. He attended Brown Preparatory School, the Institute for Colored Youth in Philadelphia, Pa., and the University of Pennsylvania. Trumbauer recognized the talent of Julian Abele when he observed some of Abele's student award winning drawings. Upon Abele's graduation in 1902 as the first African-American student in architecture at the University of Pennsylvania, Trumbauer financed further study for him at the Ecole Des Beaux Arts in Paris. Abele joined Trumbauer's firm in 1906, advancing to chief designer in 1909. Abele designed the Fifth Avenue Residence of James B. Duke in New York, and Duke soon hired Abele to design the medieval-style Gothic buildings of East and West campuses of Duke University. Abele designed over 600 buildings including the Free Library of Philadelphia. Trumbauer died in 1938; Abele and business partner William O. Frank continued to run the firm until Abele's death in 1950.
After the death of Horace Trumbauer in 1938, the firm continued for another twenty years under his name. With commissions more difficult to come by during the Great Depression and World War II, it was not a propitious time to change the name of the firm. However, Abele's name began appearing on the architectural drawings in an obvious change of policy. In 1940 when decisions were being made concerning burial in the Duke University chapel crypt, A. S. Brower, then assistant to the Comptroller, advised that Abele be consulted because he "prepared the plans and knows the details of the building better than anyone else."
[Source: Free Library of Pennsylvania]
Collection Overview
Architectural drawings and Photographs comprise the majority of the Trumbauer architectural drawings collection. The dates of this collection range from 1924 to 1952, with the bulk of material from 1926-1938. Other materials include blueprints, negatives, drawings, and reproductions.
A number of Related Collections also contain building specifications, daily work logs, financial ledgers, contracts, and general correspondence for most buildings. Correspondence (often including specifications) exchanged primarily between Horace Trumbauer, William O. Frank, Julian Abele, and Frank Clyde Brown (Duke University Comptroller), S.W. Myatt (Assistant to the President) and A.C. Lee (Chief Engineer for Duke University Building) about general construction at Duke University. Additionally, published building specifications can be found in the library catalog.
This collection brings together references to material from a variety of sources in University Archives. Most blueprints, sketches and drawings are stored flat in oversized map cabinets. Other blueprints, sketches, and drawings are folded and interfiled among established collections and within the Operations and Maintenance Department Records. General building specifications, plans for proposed buildings, daily work logs, financial ledgers, contracts, and general correspondence are located in the Operations and Maintenance Department Records, as well as the Frank C. Brown Papers. Bound volumes of published building specifications are stored in the University Archives book collection. Photographs of buildings and architectural sketches and drawings are located in the Photograph Collection. Biographical information about Horace Trumbauer and Julian Abele can be found in the Biographical Reference Collection. The Building Reference Collection contains related information about campus buildings.
Subject Headings
These and related materials may be accessed under the following subject headings in the Duke University Libraries online catalog.
Trumbauer, Horace, 1869-1938
Abele, Julian, 1881-1950.
Brown, Frank C. (Frank Clyde)
Duke Chapel (Durham, N.C.)
Duke Hospital -- Design and construction -- Planning
Duke University -- Buildings -- History
Duke University. Hospital -- Buildings -- Specifications
Duke University -- Pictorial works
African American architects -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia
Architects -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia
Architecture -- Designs and plans -- Working drawings
Campus planning -- North Carolina -- Durham
Chapels -- Designs and plans
Dormitories -- Designs and plans
Gothic revival (Architecture)--North Carolina -- Durham
College buildings -- Designs and plans
Durham (N.C.)--Buildings, structures, etc
Architectural drawings
Blueprints
Photographs
Sketches
Contents of Collection
- Architectural Drawings Series, ca. 1924-1954
  Contains oversized originals, reproductions, blueprints, drawings, and sketches. Organized by building name.
  - Art Museum [proposed]
    - Ackland Art Museum, Front Elevation, Black/white Reproduction 13" x 24" (Opaperfolder 13)
    - Ackland Art Museum, Front Elevation, Reproduction Black/white 13" x 24" (darker reproduction of above) (Opaperfolder 13)
    - Ackland Art Museum, First floor plan, undated, Original Black/white 21.5" x 28" (Opaperfolder 13)
  - Auditorium
    - Auditorium, East Elevation and Front Elevation, undated, Blueprint 18" x 24" (Opaperfolder 7)
    - Auditorium, First floor plan, undated, Blueprint 18" x 24" (Opaperfolder 7)
    - Auditorium, Basement plan, undated, Blueprint 18" x 24" (Opaperfolder 7)
  - Chapel
    - Duke Memorial Chapel, [Interior], undated, Reproduction Black/white with some color. 36" x 24" (Opaperfolder 10)
    - Duke Memorial Chapel, [Exterior], undated, Reproduction Black/white with some color. 36" x 24" (Opaperfolder 10)
    - Detail for Carved Frieze in Vestry, Amer. Oak For Duke Memoril (sic) Chapel, Durham, [N.C.], undated, Original Black/white Pencil on paper 42" x 17" (Opaperfolder 11)
    - Study of Memorial Chapel Duke University, Durham, N.C., undated, Original Framed, hanging 24" x 32"; Location: Art storage
    - View of Chapel from Campus, Original framed, 44" x 29 1/4"
    - Chapel Tower and Administration Building, Original framed, 44" x 29 1/4"
  - Chapel, Bragtown
    - Duke Chapel, M.E. Church, South Interior [View of pews] Bragtown, North Carolina, Reproduction Black/white 11" x 13.5" (Opaperfolder 15)
    - Duke Chapel M.E. Church, South Exterior Bragtown, North Carolina, Reproduction Black/white 11" x 13.5" (Opaperfolder 15)
  - Courtyard
    - Study of the Main Courtyard, undated, Reproduction Black/white Mounted 14" x 20" (Opaperfolder 8)
  - Dormitories
    - Dormitory Group [view of clock tower] Duke University, Original Framed, hanging 20" x 36"
    - Suggestion of Treatment for Dormitories, undated, Original Framed, hanging 25" x 13"
    - Sketch of the Treatment of Campus between Aycock and Jarvis Halls, undated, Original Pencil on paper Mounted 20" x 8" (Opaperfolder 14)
    - Suggested Treatment for dormitories of Trinity College, undated, Black/white Reproduction 10" x 21" (Opaperfolder 8)
    - Proposed Dormitory for Engineer Students, Coordinate College for Women, Front Elevation, Second Floor Plan, undated, Black/white Reproduction 16.5" x 12.5" (Opaperfolder 13)
    - Dormitory Group, undated (Opaperfolder 3)
  - Engineering, College of
    - Proposed Shops for the College of Engineering, Front Elevation, undated, Original Color Pastel on paper 13" x 24" (Opaperfolder 13)
    - Proposed Aeronautics and Shop Building, Ground Floor Plan, undated, Black/white Reproduction 26" x 13" (Opaperfolder 13)
    - College of Engineering, Proposed Shops, Side elevation, undated, Color Original 19" x 17" (Opaperfolder 13)
    - College of Engineering Blueprints, May 1946, Blueprint 16.5" x 8" (Opaperfolder 12)
      - Foundation plan
      - Footing, column, and beam schedule
      - First floor framing plan
      - Second floor framing plan
      - First floor plan
  - Faculty Club
    - Proposed Duke University Faculty Club, First and Second Floor Plan, February 28, 1947, Original Color 14" x 20" (Opaperfolder 13)
    - Proposed Duke University Faculty Club, [Front View], February 28, 1947, Original Color Pencil and watercolor on paper 14" x 20" (Opaperfolder 13)
    - Proposed Duke University Faculty Club, Basement Floor Plan, February 28, 1947, Original Color Pencil on paper Original 14" x 20" (Opaperfolder 13)
    - Proposed Duke University Faculty Club, View from entrance drive, February 28, 1947, Original Color Pastel on paper 9" x 15" (Opaperfolder 13)
    - Proposed Duke University Faculty Club, View from Myrtle Drive, February 28, 1947, Original Color Pastel on paper 8" x 16.5" (Opaperfolder 13)
  - Faculty Houses
    - Faculty Houses, Loft Floor Plan and Roof, Basement Floor Plan, August 19, 1930, revised January 8, 1931, Reproduction Black/white 34" x 18" (Opaperfolder 14)
    - Faculty Houses, First Floor Plan, Second Floor Plan, August 19, 1930, revised January 8, 1931, revised February 9, 1931, Reproduction Black/white 34" x 18" (Opaperfolder 14)
    - Faculty Houses, Front Elevation, Kitchen and Elevation/ Living Room Elevation, Rear Elevation, August 19, 1930, revised October 30, 1930, Reproduction Black/white 34" x 18" (Opaperfolder 14)
    - Faculty House #2 Elevation (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Faculty House #2 Ground Plan (Opaperfolder 2)
  - Forestry, School of
    - Proposed School of Forestry, Exterior view, Original Pencil on paper 17" x 8.6" (Opaperfolder 13, 14)
    - Proposed School of Forestry, Original Pencil on paper Mounted on cardboard 17" x 8.6" (Opaperfolder 13, 14)
    - Proposed School of Forestry, Front Elevation, undated, Color Original Mounted 81/2" x 15 " (Opaperfolder 13, 14)
    - Proposed School of Forestry, Front Elevation, undated, Original Pencil on paper Mounted 8.5" x 17.5" (Opaperfolder 13, 14)
  - Garden
    - Proposed Entrance to Iris Garden [Features plant details, seats, memorial tablets], undated, Reproduction Black/white 20.5" x 18" (Opaperfolder 14)
  - Library
    - Tower, Library Building [Light/chandelier], undated, Pencil on paper/watercolor 16" x 25" (Opaperfolder 6, 8)
  - Medical School
    - Medical School, undated, Original Pencil and pastel on paper 15" x 22" (Opaperfolder 8)
  - Nurses' Home
    - Proposed Nurses Home, Duke University Hospital and Medical School, February 22, 1950, Original Color Pencil and pastel on paper 13.5" x 22.5" (frame) 8" x 17" (image) (Opaperfolder 6, 8, 14)
    - Proposed Nurses Home, Front Elevation, Sept 2, 1948, Original Pastel and pencil on paper 35" x 12.5" (Opaperfolder 6, 8, 14)
    - Proposed Nurses Home, Duke University Hospital and Medical School, May 3, 1948, Original Color Pastel on paper Mounted on cardboard 15" x 6" (Opaperfolder 6, 8, 14)
  - Physics, School of
    - Proposed Building for School of Physics, Front Elevation, April 16, 1947, Original Color Pastel/Pencil on paper 29" x 8.5" (Opaperfolder 6)
  - Plaque
    - Duke University Plaque ["The aims of this University"], undated, Numbered "1". Original. Pencil and chalk on paper Mounted on cardboard Light smudging on surface Scale: 1/2 full size 17.25" x 10.5" (Opaperfolder 14)
  - Sciences Buildings
    - [Biological Sciences Building], undated, Original Pencil on paper Mounted 11.75" x 26" (Opaperfolder 8)
    - [Biological Sciences Building], undated, Reproduction Black/white 11.5" x 22.5" (Opaperfolder 8)
  - Union
    - Union Cloisters [External view], undated, Original Pencil on paper 23" x 15" (Opaperfolder 14)
  - West Campus
    - West Campus Plan, Duke University, Durham, N.C., undated, Original Framed, hanging 52" x 28"
  - Woman's College
    - View of Campus Toward Auditorium. Women's (sic) College, undated, Original Pencil on paper 36" x 24" (Opaperfolder 4)
    - Bird's Eye View Coordinate School for Women, Original framed, 28" x 41"
- Photographs Series
  Contains photographs of architectural drawings. The "p" notation after photographs indicates that there is a corresponding negative on file. Items are located in several different folders, generally organized by building name.
  Photographs can be found in Box 81 of the University Archives Photograph Collection: http://library.duke.edu/rubenstein/findingaids/uaphoto/
  - Architectural Drawings, Horace Trumbauer
    - Dormitory Group
    - View Showing Completion of Campus Enclosure by Addition of Five Buildings at Side Entrance Driveway
    - Union Cloisters
    - Station for the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad
  - Ackland Art Museum (proposed)
    - First floor plan (p84)
    - Front Elevation (p85)
  - Allen Building
    - Allen Building. Architectural Sketch. [Duke University Classroom and Administration Building]. (p97, p91)
    - Reproduction of Allen Building. Architectural Sketch. [Duke University Classroom and Administration Building].
  - Aerial View--West Campus, Plot Plan, West Campus, [August 1930]
    - Plot plan showing suggested arrangement of Duke University Buildings [at main St., Durham Blvd., and "A" St.] (p2892)
    - West Campus Plot Plan [22 buildings] (p2331)
    - Bird's Eye View of Duke University (p90)
    - Study of Proposed Buildings for Duke University (p90)
    - Study of Proposed Buildings for Duke University (p88)
    - Study of Proposed Buildings for Duke University (p89)
    - Study of Proposed Buildings for Duke University (p2332)
    - Study of Proposed Buildings for Duke University
    - Study of Proposed Buildings for Duke University (p87)
  - Baldwin Auditorium
    - View of Campus Toward Auditorium, Women's (sic) College (p2608)
  - Aerial View and Plot Plan, East (photographs) Campus
    - Birds Eye View of Girls College (p86)
  - Chapel, Exterior
    - Study for Tower, Duke memorial Chapel (p2950)
    - Chapel, rear view (p95)
    - "The Chapel campus" (postcard)
    - Chapel, side view (p94)
    - Chapel Tower, Administration Building (p2891)
    - View of Chapel from the campus (p97)
    - The Chapel (p2892)
    - The Chapel Tower and School of Religion (p96)
    - Chapel Campus [view from the quad]
  - Chapel, Interior
    - Interior of the Chapel (p93)
    - Interior of the Chapel (postcard)
  - Duke Chapel, United Methodist Church
    - Duke Chapel, M.E. Church South, Bragtown, North Carolina, Interior (p3004)
    - Duke Chapel, M.E. Church South, Bragtown, North Carolina (p3005)
  - Dining Hall, West Campus, Interior
    - Interior, West campus Dining Hall (p98)
  - Dormitory Groups, West Campus
    - West Campus Dorms--View from south (p102)
    - West Campus Dorms Group (including clock tower) (p101)
    - Typical Dormitory Group
    - South side of Dormitory Quadrangle (p104)
    - Southwest view of Dormitory Group C, West Campus (p100)
    - Suggestions for Treatment of Dormitories (p99)
    - West End of Dormitory quadrangle (p2606)
    - Duke University, for Mr. J.B. Duke. Elevation of Union and Dormitory Buildings. October 16, 1924 (p103)
  - Few Quadrangle (Group D Dormitories), Tower
    - Drawing of Graduate Dorm Tower (p3165)
  - Hospital (including Obele [sic] addition)
    - Private Patients Building (p825)
    - Private Patients Building, large format (p3165)
    - Private Patients Building, oversize negative (p3165)
    - Elevation of hospital Group [Nurses Home, Hospital, Staff, Medical School]
    - Medical School and Hospital (p105)
  - Perkins Library, West Campus
    - Library looking Toward Chapel (p106)
  - Main Court, West Campus
    - Study of Main Court (p2607)
  - Main Entrance, West Campus
    - Main Entrance (p107)
  - Indoor Stadium [Cameron]
    - [Cameron] Indoor Stadium (p92)
    - [Cameron] Indoor Stadium, large format (p3163)
  - Medical School
    - Medical School (p2609)
    - [Medical School]
  - Physics Building
    - Proposed Physics Building, Front Elevation
  - Proposed Buildings, School of Forestry
    - Proposed School of Forestry, front view (p2912)
    - Proposed School of Forestry, front view (p3162)
  - Religious Education Building
    - Chapel, Religious Education Building (p2612)
    - Religious Education Building (p2611)
  - West Campus
    - Union Looking Across main Campus (p108)
    - West Union (p2610)
  - Architectural Sketches, West Campus
    - West Campus View from South of Dorms (p102)
    - Plan Showing Proposed new Buildings [original in the Rare Books, Manuscripts, and Special Collections Library]
  - Union Cloisters, West Campus
    - Union Cloisters
  - [Wallace Wade] Stadium
    - Sketch of Stadium [April 19, 1926] (p2613)
- Related Collections
  Other archival collections containing materials related to the construction of Duke University.
  - Frank C. Brown Papers, 1899-1943
    The bulk of the material concerns the construction of Duke University's campus. It includes correspondence with the architectural firm of Horace Trumbauer, construction progress reports, diaries of trips made in 1924 and 1926 to look at other campuses, and a lantern slide presentation on the campus.
  - Operations and Maintenance Department Records, 1919-1957
    Includes records (specifications and blueprints) of renovation and remodeling projects for campus buildings.
    - Frank C. Brown Files, 1919-1941
      - Buildings (1926-1927)
        Notes from meetings between W.P. Few, Trumbauer, R.L. Flowers, and Frank C. Brown; Correspondence and notes from W.R. Perkins; Sketch of layout of campus buildings; Scale plans for campus buildings; Proposed changes and modifications between Trumbauer and Duke University
      - Dormitory Plans, no date
        Plans for Dormitories 1, 2, 3, and 4; Floor plans for Groups "A", "B", and "C"
      - Duke's Chapel [M.E. Church, Bragtown, N.C.], 1927
        General correspondence; Sketch of corner stone; General specifications
      - Trumbauer, Horace, 1926
        Correspondence about heating plant conduits
      - Trumbauer, Horace, February 1927-January 1928
        Union Building fire alarm equipment, kick plates, fire escape, flagpole, lighting, kitchen layout, garbage sorting table, plumbing; Clocks and bells in East and West campus; Blackboards; Hospital doors soundproofing; Science Building equipment
      - Trumbauer, Horace, January 1928-June 1928
        Science Building plumbing fixtures; Heating/steam lines in campus buildings; Auditorium acoustics; Soundproofing; Dr. Few's entry in Encyclopedia Britannica using images of Duke University; Paint for dormitories, classrooms, library, and science building
      - Trumbauer, Horace, July 1928-August 1937
        Auditorium picture screen; Leather covered doors; Creating a sketch of the chapel (isolated from adjoining buildings); Mantels for dining rooms (marble); Commemorative plates for buildings
      - Trumbauer, Horace, August 2, 1937
        Detailed instructions on caring for and installing stonework (written by E.H. Clement for future caretakers of stone at Duke University)
      - Trumbauer, Horace, 1938
        Future buildings; Radiators; Engineering and Fine Arts Day (University of Pennsylvania); Art Museum at Duke University
      - Work Reports, E.H. Clements Company, 1925-1927
        Worksite visits and reports of work in progress; Fireproofing in dormitories; Finishing touches in dormitories 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5
      - Work Reports, George A. Fuller Construction Company, June 1927; October-November 1927
        - Memorandum: Steel workers walking off the job
        - Memorandum: Demolition of Craven Hall
        - Memorandum: Union Building balcony corrections
        - Daily work reports of subcontractors